Guide to the Revolutionary Communist Party Records TAM.090
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Revolutionary Communist Party Records
1975-1979
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Revolutionary Communist Party, USA
TAM.090
1 Linear Feet (1 box)
The Revolutionary Communist Party (RCP) was a Maoist organization founded in 1975 as the successor to the Revolutionary Union (founded in 1968). The collection consists of central committee bulletins and position papers, as well as pamphlets, flyers, and items from related organizations of the era.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Revolutionary Communist Party (RCP) was founded in 1975 as the successor to the Revolutionary Union (founded in 1968). It was the first explicitly Maoist organization in the United States. The Party has been led by Bob Avakian since it's founding. The RCP has supported the domestic and foreign policies of The People's Republic of China until Mao's death in 1976 and opposed what they saw as revisionist, social imperialist policies of the Soviet Union.
Two years after the 1976 overthrow of the "Gang of Four" in China, the RCP split. The majority, led by Avakian, felt that the Chinese government had adopted revisionist policies, while the minority, which supported the present regime of the CCP, established the Revolutionary Workers Headquarters. The RWHq remained in the RCP for one year, then merged with the Bay Area Communist Union, the League of Revolutionary Struggle, and other organizations to form the Committee to Unite Marxists-Leninists. In the late 1970's, the RCP shifted it's concentration from heavy industry toward youth and immigrant workers.
In the mid-1970's, the Party opposed busing, affirmative action, and Black Nationalism, believing them to be non-revolutionary policies. To demonstrate against U.S. expansionist policies they briefly occupied the Alamo. They were instrumental in the organization of the National United Workers Organization and the Unemployed Workers Organizing Committee. In 1982, after a three-year court battle, 17 members, the "Mao Tse Tung defendants", were acquitted of felony charges for allegedly violent activity at a demonstration in Washington, D.C. In 1989 the RCP won a supreme court ruling that flag burning falls under protection of the first amendment. Since 1975, they have published The Worker.
Scope and Content Note
The collection of the Revolutionary Communist Party provides significant documentation of the Party's activities. The 1.00 linear foot collection spans the years 1970-1983, with the bulk of material spanning 1976-1979. It consists of internal documents including central committee bulletins and position papers, as well as pamphlets, and flyers. Also included in the collection are items from related organizations and other left organizations of this era.
The collection is organized into seven series. Series I, Origins, contains items about the Revolutionary Union and it's evolution into the Party. Series II, National Organization, consists of internal documents and bulletins issued by or to the central committee. Series III contains internal documents issued by or to the district and local organizations. Series IV consists of flyers and other materials documenting the Party's political activities, campaigns, and events. Series V, Topical Files, principally contains position papers dealing with Party issues; many are from members. Series VI, Related Organizations, contains items from other organizations, including the Revolutionary Workers Headquarters, which had members join or leave the RCP. Series VII, Publications, consists of pamphlets and bulletins published by the RCP or the RWHq. Series I and II are arranged chronologically. Series III through VII are arranged alphabetically.
The collection provides good documentation on the political activities and positions of the RCP, but documentation of the RCP post-1980 is sparse. Many of the materials are undated, and there is no mention of individual members except of the chairman, Bob Avakian.
Arrangement
Folders are generally arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 7 series:
Missing Title
I: Origins
II: National Organization
III: District/Local
IV: Political Activity
V: Topical Files
VI: Related Organizations
VII: Publications
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The provenance of this collection is unknown. The accession number associated with this collection is 1993.006.
African Americans -- Civil rights -- United States.; Women's rights -- United States.; Correspondence.; Fliers (printed matter); News bulletins.; Pamphlets.; Communism and culture -- United States.; Communism -- United States.; Avakian, Bob; Revolutionary Communist Party, USA. Central Committee; League of Revolutionary Struggle (M-L); Revolutionary Workers Headquarters of the RCP; Revolutionary Communist Party, USA
- Series I: Origins
  - Revolutionary Union, 1973-1975, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - BARU (Bay Area Revolutionary Union), undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bulletin on Formation of Party, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Founding Conference-Main Report, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Series II: National Organization
  - Central Committee Reports, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - National Bulletins, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Notes, 1977-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bookstore, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series III: District/Local
  - District Bulletins, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - District Reports, 1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - New York-New Jersey, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Philadelphia, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Pittsburgh, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series IV: Political Activity
  - African Liberation Day Campaign, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Conference on War and the International Situation, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Eagle Strike, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - International Women's Day, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - July 4th, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - May Day, 1976-1981, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Mao Tsetung Defendents, 1981-1982, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Miscellaneous Activity, 1975-1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - New York City Campaigns, 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Series V: Topical Files
  - Trade Union Strategy and Work, 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Black Liberation Struggle, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bob Avakian, 1976-1983 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - China, 1975-1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cuba, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Discussion and Position Papers, 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - E.R.A. and the Women Question, 1974, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Middle East, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous Topics, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - National Question, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Song Workshop, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Study Guides, 1977, undated (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Series VI: Related Organizations
  - National United Workers Organization, undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - RWHq (Revolutionary Workers Headquarters), 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Youth Organization, 1975-1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Unemployed Workers Organizing Committee, 1976, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - BACU (Bay Area Communist Union), 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - International Socialists, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - John Brown Revolutionary League, 1970-1971, undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - New York Communist Workers Organization, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Series VII: Publications
  - Pamphlets, 1976-1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - The Worker (RWHq), undated (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - The Workers Voice, 1979, undated (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Struggle, Criticism, and Unity (RWHq), 1978, undated (Box 1, Folder 46)